Jubal Anderson Early Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Jubal Anderson Early Papers 1829-1930
MSS19356
Early, Jubal Anderson, 1816-1894
5,000 items
16 containers plus 2 oversize
9 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States and Confederate Army officer, lawyer, and state legislator of Virginia. Correspondence, diaries, military papers, speeches and articles, clippings, a scrapbook, printed matter, and maps dated largely after the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893--Correspondence.; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893.; Cabell, Henry Ann, approximately 1784-1843--Correspondence.; Cabell, John J., 1772-1834--Correspondence.; Colston, Raleigh Edward, 1825-1896.--Correspondence.; Daniel, John W. (John Warwick), 1842-1910--Correspondence.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889--Correspondence.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889--Family.; Davis, Varina, 1826-1906--Correspondence.; Early, Jubal Anderson, 1816-1894.; Evans, Clement A. (Clement Anselm), 1833-1911.; Hays, Harry T. (Harry Thompson), 1820-1876.; Hill, D. H. (Daniel Harvey), 1821-1889--Correspondence.; Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863--Correspondence.; Johnson, Bradley T. (Bradley Tyler), 1829-1903--Correspondence.; Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston), 1807-1891--Correspondence.; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905--Correspondence.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870--Correspondence.; Maury, Dabney Herndon, 1822-1900--Correspondence.; Mosby, John Singleton, 1833-1916--Correspondence.; Trimble, Isaac Ridgeway, 1802-1888.; Van Dorn, Earl, 1820-1863--Correspondence.
Organizations
Confederate States of America. Army of Northern Virginia.; Confederate States of America. Army--Officers.; Southern Historical Society.; United States Military Academy.; United States. Army--Officers.
Subjects
Bull Run, 1st Battle of, Va., 1861.; Bull Run, 2nd Battle of, Va., 1862.; Gettysburg Campaign, 1863.; Lotteries--Louisiana.; Mine Run Campaign, Va., 1863.; Practice of law--Virginia.; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877); Shenandoah Valley Campaign, 1864 (August-November); Shenandoah Valley Campaign, 1864 (May-August); Williamsburg, Battle of, Williamsburg, Va., 1862.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; Virginia--Politics and government.; Washington (D.C.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Titles
Jubal Anderson Early Papers at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Army officers, Confederate.; Lawyers.; Legislators--Virginia.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Jubal Anderson Early, army officer, lawyer, and state legislator of Virginia, were given to the Library of Congress in 1923 by A. S. Perham and Ruth H. Early. Additional materials were given in 1932 and 1934 by Evelyn R. Early; in 1966 by Henrianne C. Early, and in 1992 by T. Keister Greer. Further material was purchased in 1932.
Transfers
Some maps have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division where they are identified as part of the Jubal Anderson Early Papers.
Related Materials
Significant collections of Early’s papers can also be found at the Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Virginia; the Huntington Library, San Marino, California; Jones Memorial Library, Lynchburg, Virginia; and the National Archives and Records Administration, Washington, D.C.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Jubal Anderson Early are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The Jubal Anderson Early Papers are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000090. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1816, Nov. 3 Born, Rocky Mount, Va.
1837 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1837 1838 Officer, Third Artillery, United States Army Served in Seminole Wars
1838 Resigned, United States Army
1840 Admitted to the bar of Virginia
1846 1848 Major, First Virginia Regiment, United States Army Served in Mexican War
1861 Colonel, Confederate States of America Army Organized volunteers in Lynchburg, Va.
1862 Wounded, Battle of Williamsburg, Va.
1863 Promoted to major general
1864 Conducted operations in Maryland and near Washington, D.C.
1865 Moved to Mexico
1865 1869 Lived in Canada
1866 Published A Memoir of the Last Year of the War of Independence, in the Confederate States of America. Toronto: Lovell & Gibson
1870 Resumed law practice, Lynchburg, Va.
1877 Commissioner, Louisiana lottery
1894, Mar. 2 Died, Lynchburg, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jubal Anderson Early (1816-1894) span the years 1829-1930 and include correspondence, diaries, military papers, speeches and articles, clippings, a scrapbook, printed matter, and maps relating to his military, legal, and political careers.
The papers are divided into three series, Chronological File, Addition, and Oversize. Material prior to the Civil War reflects Early’s years as a cadet at the United States Military Academy, his army service, law practice, and Virginia political activities. Included are letters from John J. Cabell to his wife Henry Ann Cabell. Papers relating to Early’s experiences during the Civil War include items concerning his participation in the battles of First Bull Run and Williamsburg, the Gettysburg Campaign, and the Shenandoah Valley Campaign of 1864. Also in the papers are a report on the performance of General Isaac Trimble’s brigade in the Battle of Second Bull Run, reports by Generals Harry T. Hays and Clement A. Evans on skirmishes in the Mine Run Campaign, a list of units in G. T. Beauregard’s I Corps, Army of Northern Virginia (1862), and a return of troops commanded by Joseph E. Johnston in the spring of 1862. Postwar material, which comprises the bulk of the collection, includes papers on Early’s business affairs, especially the Louisiana lottery, his activities at the Southern Historical Society, and aid extended to Confederate families, including that of Jefferson Davis.
Correspondents include G. T. Beauregard, Raleigh E. Colston, John W. Daniel, Jefferson Davis, Varina Davis, Daniel Harvey Hill, Stonewall Jackson, Bradley T. Johnson, Joseph E. Johnston, Fitzhugh Lee, Robert E. Lee, Dabney Herndon Maury, John Singleton Mosby, and Earl Van Dorn.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Chronological File, 1829-1911
Addition, 1833-1930
Oversize, 1833-1930
Container List
Selections available on microfilm. Shelf no. 4,221.
- Chronological File, 1829-1911 (Box 1-15)
  Correspondence, military papers, and other material.
  Arranged chronologically in bound volumes.
  - 1829, Dec. 21-1841, Oct. 23 (Box 1)
  - 1841, Dec. 2-1861, Jan. 21 (Box 2)
  - 1861, Mar. 15-1862, Oct. 30 (Box 3)
  - 1863, Jan. 7-1867, Nov. 25 (Box 4)
  - 1868, Feb. 7-1876, Apr. 24 (Box 5)
  - 1871, May 6-1873, Apr. 29 (Box 6)
  - 1873, May 5-1875, Sept. 30 (Box 7)
  - 1875, Oct. 2-1876, Dec. 29 (Box 8)
  - 1877, Jan. 3-1878, Apr. 20 (Box 9)
  - 1878, May 2-1880, Apr. 19 (Box 10)
  - 1880, May 1-1882, Dec. 31 (Box 11)
  - 1883, Jan. 9-1884, July 20 (Box 12)
  - 1884, Aug. 4-1888, Feb. 20 (Box 13)
  - 1888, Mar. 3-1891, July 29 (Box 14)
  - 1891, Aug. 10-1911, July 13, undated (Box 15)
- Addition, 1833-1930 (Box 16)
  Correspondence, a diary, military papers, printed matter, a scrapbook, and speeches and writings.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Correspondence and military papers (Box 16)
    - 1847-1848, 1861 (Box 16)
    - 1862-1915, undated (Box 16)
  - Diary, 1865 (Box 16)
  - Lists, undated (Box 16)
  - Printed matter, 1866-1911, undated (Box 16)
  - Scrapbook, 1833-1930 See Oversize (Box 16)
  - Speeches and writings, undated (Box 16)
    - 1 of 2 (Box 16)
    - 2 of 2 (Box 16)
- Oversize, 1833-1930 (Box OV 1-OV 2)
  Scrapbook
  - Addition (Box OV 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1833-1930 (Container 16) (Box OV 1)
      - Part I (Box OV 1)
      - Part II (Box OV 2)